{"tossups": [{"question": "This man built a gigantic bridge over the Bay of Baiae to prove to a soothsayer he could ride a horse over the bay. This man\u2019s predecssor was smothered by the Praetorian Prefect Macro. This emperor ordered an invasion of Britain that ended with his men collecting sea shells instead. Suetonius claimed that this man planned to make his horse Incitatus consul. The nickname \u201cLittle Soldier\u2019s Boot\u201d was given to, for ten points, what insane Roman emperor?", "answer": "<b> Caligula</b> (accept<b> Gaius Caesar</b>; accept<b> Gaius Julius Caesar Augustus Germanicus</b>; do not prompt on Caesar alone)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "One of these phenomena, nicknamed the \u201cmud-eater\u201d for its effects on Provence\u2019s agriculture, is known as the mistral. William of Orange\u2019s invasion of England was enabled by a so-called \u201cProtestant\u201dversion of this phenomenon, which also destroyed Philip II\u2019s Armada, preventing a Spanish takeover. The Portuguese used the term \u201cvolto de mar\u201d to describe their caravels being powered by, for ten points, what meteorological phenomenon that powers sailing ships?", "answer": "<b> wind</b>s (accept close equivalents like<b> storm</b>, but not \u201crain\u201d; accept<b> mistral</b> before mentioned; accept Protestant<b> wind</b> after \u201cWilliam\u201d is mentioned; accept trade<b>wind</b>s after \u201cvolto\u201d is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "Debate over this action was triggered by a plan to give Lorenzo Thomas a job. Prominent advocates for this action included John Bingham and an ailing Thaddeus Stevens. Edmund Ross earned a chapter of John F. Kennedy\u2019s<em> Profiles in Courage</em> for casting the deciding vote against this action, which was a response to a violation of the Tenure of Office Act. The attempted firing of Edwin Stanton triggered, for ten points, what Congressional event that sought to remove Abraham Lincoln\u2019s successor from office?", "answer": "<b> impeach</b>ing Andrew<b> Johnson</b> (prompt on partial answers, such as \u201cimpeachment\u201d and answers related to \u201cremoving Andrew Johnson (from the Presidency)\u201d) Page 1", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A symbol of authority possessed by the holder of this position was a set of nine cauldrons, or ding. A group of five legendary holders of this position are paired with the Three Sovereigns in many ancient texts, and the most prominent member of that group is usually named after the color yellow. The holder of this position was given the right and ability to rule from a divine provenance, which was called the Mandate of Heaven. For ten points, name this position held by monarchs from the Han Dynasty.", "answer": "<b> Emperor of China</b> (accept equivalents such as<b> king of China</b> or<b> ruler of China</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "One of these objects designed by Robert Moses was partially built using wartime rubble from England. Andrew Jackson vetoed a bill that would have created one of these structures named for Maysville, which would have been part of the Cumberland System. After his positive experience with the Autobahn, Dwight Eisenhower ordered the construction of, for ten points, what type of transportation infrastructure whose American examples include I-95 and Route 66?", "answer": "<b> road</b>s (accept specific answers, like<b> highway</b>s or<b> turnpike</b>s, etc.; accept FDR<b> Drive</b>; accept Maysville<b> Road</b>; accept Cumberland<b> Road</b>; accept<b> Interstate</b> system, Interstate<b> Highway</b> system, etc.)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Emmanuel de Roug\u00b4e coined the term for these people, who are depicted on the Medinet Habu temple. Fighting these people at the Battle of Djahy and the Battle of the Delta caused the depletion of Ramesses III\u2019s treasury. The invasions of these people may have been caused by a famine in Anatolia, though they may also have been Philistines or Minoans fleeing a volcanic eruption. The Bronze Age Collapse was caused by, for ten points, what invaders of the New Kingdom of Egypt that came from the Mediterranean?", "answer": "<b> Sea People</b>s", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "To prepare for this battle, the winning commander designed a namesake \u201cchequer\u201d of yellow and black lines to better identify his ships. A tactic mirroring John Jervis\u2019 maneuvers at Cape St. Vincent was employed at this battle to isolate the<em> Bucentaure</em>. The destruction of a Franco-Spanish navy at this battle ended Napoleon\u2019s hopes of invading England. For ten points, name this 1805 victory for Lord Nelson, commemorated in a namesake London Square.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Trafalgar</b> Page 2", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man was nearly assassinated by the Italian anarchist Gennaro Rubino in 1902. This ruler attempted to abolish the military policy of<em> Remplacement</em> after his country\u2019s neutrality was tenuously preserved in the Franco-Prussian War. This ruler earned the nickname the \u201cBuilder King\u201d for his public works projects, including the Antwerpen-Centraal Railway Station. He commissioned Henry Stanley to lay claims to colonial territory in Africa; that territory later became the Congo Free State. For ten points, name this Belgian monarch.", "answer": "King<b> Leopold II</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Iconic photos from this site include a snapshot of Zbigniew Brzezinski [z\u2019big-nee-ev breh-ZHIN-skee] playing chess and Paul Vathis\u2019 \u201cSerious Steps\u201d showing John F. Kennedy and Dwight Eisenhower walking side by side. This site\u2019s Dogwood, Aspen and Laurel buildings have been used to house visitors like Anwar Sadat and Menachem Begin, who met on a 1979 retreat. For ten points, name this Presidential compound where Jimmy Carter helped broker a peace accord between Egypt and Israel.", "answer": "<b> Camp David</b> (accept<b> N</b>aval<b> S</b>upport<b> F</b>acility<b> Thurmont</b>; accept<b> Shangri-La</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This rebellion\u2019s leader issued a manifesto criticizing the Green Springs monopoly on the beaver trade. This rebellion\u2019s planners achieved success in an attack on the Susquehannock, but John Ingram was forced to take command after this rebellion\u2019s leader died of dysentery. This rebellion was sparked by settlers who felt that the colonial government did not do enough to prevent attacks by natives. Jamestown was burned down as a result of, for ten points, what 1676 rebellion in Virginia?", "answer": "<b> Bacon</b>\u2019s Rebellion", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "These people \u201ctrampled on the bodies of saints [...] like dung in the streets,\u201d according to Alcuin\u2019s description of their raid on Lindisfarne. These people were recruited to form the Varangian Guard by the Byzantines. Charles the Simple signed the Treaty of Saint-Claire-sur-Epte, granting these people land in Western Europe, and they were granted Normandy after carrying out a series of raids down the Seine River in their longships. For ten points, name these seafaring marauders from Scandinavia who didn\u2019t actually wear iconic two-horned caps.", "answer": "<b> Viking</b>s (prompt on Scandinavians or Norse before \u201cScandinavia\u201d is read)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This Chief Justice wrote that the power to determine whether a state government was a \u201clegitimate republican\u201d one was a political question in<em> Luther v. Borden</em>. This Chief Justice at the time of the<em> Amistad</em> case also wrote a controversial opinion denying the plaintiff standing on account of his race and ruling the Missouri Compromise unconstitutional. The<em> Dred Scott v. Sanford</em> case was decided by, for ten points, what Chief Justice who presided from 1836 to 1864?", "answer": "Roger<b> Taney</b> ([taw-nee], but be lenient)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This musician paid tribute to the head of the African National Congress in \u201cFull Nelson.\u201d The wife of Akhnaten lent her name to this man\u2019s final all-acoustic album,<em> Nefertiti</em>, which featured Wayne Shorter and Herbie Hancock as part of his \u201csecond great quintet.\u201d A 1957 compilation album by this man\u2019s nonet lent its name to a genre that succeeded bebop.<em> Birth of the Cool</em> was performed by, for ten points, what jazz trumpeter who recorded<em> Kind of Blue</em>?", "answer": "Miles<b> Davis</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This scientist\u2019s namesake constant is equal to the time derivative of the scale factor over the scale factor, and the reciprocal of that constant is equal to the age of the Universe.</b> <b>This man\u2019s namesake (+)</b> <b>law, which was discovered while working at the Mount Wilson</b> <b>Observatory, states that the recessional velocity of a galaxy is proportional to its distance from us; that implies the occurrence of the Big Bang. The \u201cPillars of Creation\u201d (*) </b>photograph was taken by a device named for, for ten points, what American astronomer who names a space telescope launched in 1990?", "answer": "Edwin<b> Hubble</b> (accept<b> Hubble</b> constant,<b> Hubble</b>\u2019s Law, and/or<b> Hubble</b> Space Telescope)", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Astronomy"}, {"question": "<b>This speech laments how the \u201csolitary inventor...has been overshadowed by scientists\u201dand calls on Americans to avoid \u201cplundering for our own ease and convenience...the precious</b> <b>resources of tomorrow.\u201d This speech warns against allowing (+)</b> <b>\u201cpublic policy\u201d to fall</b> <b>in the hands of the \u201cscientific-technological elite\u201d and warns against the \u201cunwarranted influence\u201d of the (*)</b> \u201cmilitary-industrial complex.\u201d For ten points, name this speech, given three days before John F. Kennedy\u2019s inaugural address, that ended a US President\u2019s public career.", "answer": "Dwight<b> Eisenhower</b>\u2019s<b> Farewell</b> Address (accept descriptive answers of Dwight<b> Eisenhower</b>\u2019s <b>last speech</b> as President)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>A state named for this modern-day country existed for twenty-four hours under president Avgustyn Voloshyn. Symon Petliura led another state in this modern-day country, which</b> <b>was the site of an anti-Semitic nationalist movement led by Stepan (+)</b> <b>Bandera during</b> <b>World War II. Leonid Kuchma was overthrown as this country\u2019s President in the 2004 (*) </b>Orange Revolution, and this country was also the site of more recent Euromaidan protests. For ten points, name this country that lost control over the Crimean Peninsula after a 2014 Russian annexation.", "answer": "<b> Ukraine</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>In 1968, a consolidation process in this state\u2019s Duval County created what was briefly the largest city by land area in the US. The 2010 census recorded just 10 permanent residents in this state\u2019s city of Lake Buena Vista, a small company town adjacent to (+) Kissimmee. Pedro Me\u00b4ndez de Avil\u00b4es founded the oldest continuously occupied European settlement in the US in 1565 in what is now this state. This state\u2019s city of Titusville has suffered economically since the end of the (*)</b> Space Shuttle program. St. Augustine is in, for ten points, what southern US state whose largest by area is Jacksonville?", "answer": "<b> Florida</b> Page 9", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b>This country\u2019s Liberal and Conservative parties agreed to trade off the presidency in a 16-year period called the National Front. The M-19 guerrilas became active in this country after Gustavo Rojas Pinilla lost a 1970 election. In 2016, this country\u2019s president won the</b> <b>(+)</b> <b>Nobel Peace Prize for brokering a peace deal that this country\u2019s people rejected in a</b> <b>referendum. This country was the base of power of the Medellin (*)</b> Cartel, which ran the drug trade under Pablo Escobar. FARC rebels once fought in, for ten points, what country led by Juan Manuel Santos from Bogota?", "answer": "<b> Colombia</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>Charles Ruthenberg organized a parade in Cleveland to protest the jailing of this man. This man, one of the many co-founders of the Industrial Workers of the World, was defended</b> <b>by Clarence Darrow for his actions in the (+)</b> <b>Pullman Strike. This man declared \u201cwhen</b> <b>Pullman Strike. This man declared \u201cwhen</b> <b>I rise it will be with the ranks, and not from the ranks\u201d in a speech in (*)</b> <b>I rise it will be with the ranks, and not from the ranks\u201d in a speech in (*)</b> Canton, Ohio protesting the World War I draft. For ten points, name this five-time Socialist presidential candidate who ran his last campaign in 1920 from a prison cell.", "answer": "Eugene V.<b> Debs</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}